Dr. Irvin M. Borish Papers, 1939-1996
University of Houston Libraries
Dr. Irvin M. Borish Papers
1939-1996
Borish, Irvin M.
In 1982 Dr. Irvin Borish assumed the Benedict Professorship of Optometric Practice at the University of Houston. The University of Houston College of Optometry established the Irvin M. Borish Chair in Optometric Practice in 1987. This endowed chair carries more than one million dollars of support. The papers of Dr. Irvin Borish contain manuscripts, patents, awards and notices, conference proceedings, print items, correspondence, photographs, as well as audio and video recordings.
1997-001
9 Boxes; 5 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Biographical Note
Irvin M. Borish was born on January 21, 1913 in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, the son a Lithuanian Jewish immigrants. His father later contracted tuberculosis, forcing the family to move to Liberty, New York, where Borish graduated from Liberty High School. He returned to Philadelphia in 1930 to pursue studies in English literature at Temple University. In 1932 he enrolled in the Northern Illinois College of Optometry in Chicago.
Dr. Borish graduated from Northern Illinois College of Optometry in 1935 and achieved the best academic record in the institution's history. During the same year, the Northern Illinois College of Optometry also appointed him to the position of Instructor on the school's faculty as well as Chief of Staff for the college's Eye Clinic. By 1942, Dr. Borish held the position of Assistant Dean.
In 1944 Borish moved to Kokomo, Indiana where he started a successful private optometric practice. A heart attack in 1973 forced him to retire from private practice. After recovering, he assumed a full-time faculty position at Indiana University's Optometry School. Between the 1944 and 1973 he actively pursued many endeavors. In 1948 the first of numerous editions of Clinical Refraction, still a standard for optometry students, was published. While in private practice, Borish lobbied for the establishment of an optometry school in Bloomington, Indiana, wrote nearly one hundred articles, delivered numerous lectures, served as a visiting professor to at least nine optometry schools, and patented hard toric and bifocal contact lenses. He also contributed to the by-laws establishing the Association of Schools and Colleges of Optometry, coauthored the original manual of Accreditation used by the Council on Education and Accreditation in Optometry, as well as working on the by-laws of the Contact Lens Manufacturers Association which sets standards for the safe manufacture of contact lenses.
Dr. Borish retired from Indiana University in 1982, at which time he assumed the Benedict Professorship of Optometric Practice at the University of Houston. Since his arrival at the University of Houston, the University of Houston College of Optometry has established the Irvin M. Borish Chair in Optometric Practice (1987), an endowed chair with more than one million dollars of support. In 1995, Indiana University honored him by establishing the Borish Center for Ophthalmic Research.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Dr. Irvin Borish contain manuscripts, patents, awards and notices, conference proceedings, print items, correspondence, photographs, as well as audio and video recordings. Items in the collection date from 1937 to 1996 with most of the material dating from the late 1970s and 1980s. The majority of the material in the collection contains articles and other manuscript items written by Borish. However, the collection also contains numerous photographs, most of which are not labeled. Patent information and letters from prominent optometrists and ophthalmologists regarding Clinical Refraction might also be of interest to the researcher.
The University of Houston College of Optometry displays several of Dr. Borish's awards, honorary degrees, certificates, and other memorabilia (including a painting by him) in the Irvin M. Borish Reading Room located in the Optometry Library.
Dr. Borish's papers are arranged into twelve series: Résumé, Manuscripts, Patents, Awards and Notices, Conferences, Optometric Delegations, Print Items, Correspondence, Scrapbooks, Photographs, Audio Recordings, Video Recordings, and Miscellaneous. Original arrangement has been adhered to where possible. Subject file titles within the various series reflect titles created by Dr. Borish. Material arrangement, other than series arrangement, follows a chronological scheme whenever possible with the exception of the Manuscripts series. Subject files within the Manuscripts series are arranged alphabetically, with items in each subject file chronologically ordered.
Acquisition
Donation from Dr. Borish, 1997
Index Terms
Terms are either Library of Congress Subject Headings or taken from local sources.
Subjects (Persons)
Borish, Irvin M.
Subjects (Organizations)
University of Houston. College of Optometry.; University of Houston
Subjects
University of Houston History; Optometry schools United States; Optometry Study and teaching.
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Detailed Description
- Résumé
  There is one folder in this series, which contains Dr. Borish's 1996 résumé along with a letter to Suzanne Ferimer, Optometry Librarian at the University of Houston College of Optometry's Library.
  - Résumé and Material Accompanying Collection, April 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Manuscripts
  This series is the largest in the collection with eighty-seven folders. The materials date from 1939 to 1995. Items within this series vary considerably in content, however, most are articles, chapters, lectures, or notes. Subject files are arranged alphabetically and retain titles used by Dr. Borish.
  - Academy Editorial, March 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Academy and Professionalism, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Accommodation and Refractive Error, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Accreditation and Residents, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Amos Book Introduction, 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - AOA Long Range Planning Committee, September 1984-January 1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Aphakia Interview Contact World, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Aphakic Vision, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - ASCO RE Title VII of PHS Act, May 1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bichrome Tests, 1973-1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bifocal Contacts, Bennett Book, February 1984-September 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bifocal Contacts, Bennett Book, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bifocal Contact Lenses AOA Journal, March 1982 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Blueprint for Success - Opt Management, April 1988 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Borish Nearpoint Chart, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - By-Laws and Constitution Association of Schools and Colleges of Optometry, 1939-1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Commencement Address Pennsylvania, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Commencement Address Southern California, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Commencement Address SUNY, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Comparison Acceptance PAL vs. Bifocal - Hitzeman, May 1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Comparison Fitting 2 Types Gel Lenses, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Comparison Fitting 2 Types Gel Lenses, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Corneal Thickness Changes with Toric Soft Lenses with Soni, May 1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Corneal Thickness Changes with Toric Soft Lenses with Soni, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Don't Leave a Vacuum, 1991, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Double Masked Study - Hitzeman/Brookman, October 1980 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Editorial in Eye on Education, March 1992 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Effect of Plus Lenses on Childrens Reading Ability - with Jim Koetting, May 1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Effect of Plus Lenses on Childrens Reading Ability - with Jim Koetting, July-September 1988 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - External Clinics Adjunct Assignment, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Fitting Contact Lens Bifocals, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Fitting Contact Lens Bifocals, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Fitting Contact Lens Bifocals, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - I.B.B. Speech, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Icling Lens, October 1962 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Icling Lens, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Icling Lens, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Icling Lens, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Keratoconus (Contact Lens Forum), undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Keynote Speech IOOL, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Learning from the Past, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Liposition Finished Manuscript, March 1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Manual of Accreditation, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Max Schapero Lecture, December 1987 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Max Schapero Lecture, December 1987-March 1988 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Milestones in Optics, March 1991 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Monocular Case Differential Analysis, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Morgan Memorial Lecture, April 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Notes on Refraction Management, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Observations of Bifocal Contact Lenses - Perrigin, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Observation Operation Contact Lens Bifocals, August 1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Old Case Analysis Paper, March-September 1945 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Ophthalmology and Optometry, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Optometry in Foreign Countries, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Optometry's Premise Legal Panel in New Orleans, December 1971-February 1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Pennsylvania Externship, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Perspective on Worldwide Optometry, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Perceptual Problems in Aphakia, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Perceptual Problems in Aphakia - Diagrams, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Physiology of Ageing and Its Influence Contact Lens Prescription with Benjamin, November 1990-October 1991 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Policoff Tribute, December 1976, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Position of Contact Lenses in the Eye, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Positioning of Contact Lenses in the Eye, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Presbyopia and Contact Lenses, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Problems in Progressive Lens Placement (Brooks), undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Progressive Lenses vs. Other Forms Bifocals, December 1984-November 1989 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Pupil Dependency - Bifocal Contact Lenses, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Referral Relationships Article, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Reflections on Practice Today Optometry Management, April-November 1987 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Reflections on Practice Today Optometry Management, 1988, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Refraction Lecture for Japan, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Relation of Visual Science to Refractive Procedures, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Relative Movement of Lower Lid with Dr. Perrigin, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Report on Central and Peripheral Corneal Thickness with Soni, May 1979 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Review of Ball's Article, September 1992 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Review of NIH Allen Grant, 1982-1988, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Rigid Bifocal C.L. with Leach, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Satire on OEP, March 1950 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Spectacles as a part of Optometry Forum at Academy 1995, May 1995 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - St. Louis Talk on Contact Lenses, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Student Procurement, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Subjective Chapter - Miller, 1990-1991, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Summary Speech Tucson Planning Conference, January 1975, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Summary Speech Tucson Planning Conference, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Survey of Well-Known Systems of Fitting Small Lenses, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Survey on C.L. Presbyopia with W.B. Baldwin, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Talk to Corning on Contacts, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Textbook Contact Lens Practice with Benjamin, December 1988-September 1990 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Patents
  There are five folders in this series which contain material from 1960 to 1989. Items in this series include copies of original patent registration forms (both illustrations and written descriptions). A series of black and white photographs located in the Photographs series (Box 9, Folders 14-21), although unidentified, likely relate to the items patented.
  - Stock Agreements, December 1960 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Number 3,238,676 - Method for Altering the Power of a Corneal Contact Lens, March 1966 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Number 3,360,889 - Method for Altering the Power of a Corneal Contact Lens, January 1968 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Number 3,430,391 - Apparatus for Altering the Power of a Corneal Contact Lens, March 1969 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Indiana Contact Lens Balance Sheets, August 1988-March 1989 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Awards and Notices
  There are twenty-one folders in this series with items dating from 1944 to 1996. Subject files include assorted Awards and Notices, Certificates, Educational and Licence Certificates, and Honorary Degrees. The Irvin M. Borish Reading Room in the University of Houston's Optometry Library also displays several of Dr. Borish's awards and achievements.
  - Awards and Notices, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Awards and Notices, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Awards and Notices, 1973-1977 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Awards and Notices, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Awards and Notices, 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Awards and Notices, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Awards and Notices, 1991-1996 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Awards and Notices, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Photos, 1968-1990, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Certificates, 1963-1979 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Certificates, 1980-1988, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Certificates (Oversize), 1944-1987 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Certificates and Letters - Indiana, Houston, Other, 1970-1987, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Membership Certificates, 1979-1985, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Educational and Licence Certificates, 1956-1995 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Honorary Degrees, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Honorary Degrees, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Honorary Degrees, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Honorary Degrees, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Honorary Degrees, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Awards and Notices, April 1990 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Awards and Notices, May 1990 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Conferences
  The five folders in this series contain items dating from 1966 to 1992. Programs from various conferences are included in this series.
  - Programs, 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Programs, 1972-1978 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Programs, 1980-1985 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Programs, 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Programs, 1990-1992, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Optometric Delegations
  The nine folders in this series hold material from two international optometric delegations headed by Dr. Borish. The two subject files, India and China, represent items associated from these delegations from 1985 through 1988.
  - India - Journal, March-April 1987 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - India (India Elite School - Dr. Badranath), 1987 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - India (India Elite School - Dr. Badranath), March-September 1987 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - India - List, October 1987 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - India - Correspondence, Jun. 1987-May 1988 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - China - Ophthalmologist List, October 1985-January 1988 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - China - Project History, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - China - Material Included with Project History, January 1986-October 1988 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - China - Material Included with Project History, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Print Items
  There are twelve folders in this series with material dating from 1937 to 1996. Items in this series contain various print items, newspaper clippings, and different optometric journals. The majority of articles were either authored by Dr. Borish or written about him.
  - Print Items, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Print Items, 1955-1978 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Print Items, 1980-1985 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Print Items, 1986-1989 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Print Items, 1990-1996 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Print Items, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1963-1978 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1980-1987, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Journals, 1982-1983 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Journals, 1987-1989 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Journals, 1991-1996 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Journals, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Correspondence
  The thirty-three folders in this series contain correspondence dating from 1946 to 1994. Subject files include letters received concerning Clinical Refraction, general correspondence, as well as more personal correspondence (retirement and sympathy cards regarding Dr. Borish's heart attack). The Letters of Recommendation subject file comprises of the largest subject file in the series.
  - Clinical Refraction, 1946-1949 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Clinical Refraction, 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Clinical Refraction, 1962-1980 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - General, 1973-1980 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - General, 1981-1984 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - General, 1986-1989 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - General, 1990-1996 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - General, undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Retirement, 1983, undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Letters of Recommendation
    - Dr. William Baldwin, August 1984 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Dr. Richard Ball, March 1993 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Dr. Caroline Begley, September 1991 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Dr. Al Bucar, January 1994 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Dr. Lena Chu, September 1986 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Dr. Glenn Fry, July 1987 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Dr. Henry Hofstetter, January 1991 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Dr. Richard Hopping, April 1988 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Dr. Patricia Keach, August 1985 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Dr. David Loshin, October 1991 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Dr. Gerald Lowther, February 1988 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Dr. Morris C. McKee, January 1985 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Dr. Raymond I. Myers, March 1987 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Dr. Donald Pitts, May 1986 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Dr. Kenneth Poise, December 1991 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Dr. Maurice Poster, July 1985 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Dr. Lewis Scott, December 1981 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Dr. P. Sarita Soni, Aug. 1991 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Dr. B. Leonard Werner, July 1988 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Dr. Melvin Wolfberg, May 1989 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Dr. Dennis Yamamoto, July 1988 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Cards Regarding Heart Attack, 1971-1985 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Cards Regarding Heart Attack, undated (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Cards Regarding Heart Attack, undated (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Scrapbooks
  There are five folders in this series. Materials, dating from 1954 to 1989, focus on three areas: Presentation for Distinguished Professorship at Indiana University, the University of Houston's Borish Chair in Optometry, and a photo album containing pictures from an optometric conference in Japan. The scrapbooks remain intact to preserve their original organization while items placed in them loosely have been removed and labeled accordingly.
  - Presentation for Distinguished Professorship at Indiana University, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Material Contained in Presentation for Distinguished Professorship at Indiana University, 1954-1980, undated (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - UH Borish Chair in Optometry, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Material Contained in UH Borish Chair in Optometry, 1987-1989, undated (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Japan - Conference (Oversize), undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Photographs
  There are fifty-three photographs in this series, with items dating from 1951 to 1996. The majority of the photos are neither identified nor dated.
  - Photos, 1951-1996, undated (Box 9, Folder 1-53)
- Audio Recordings
  This series contains four cassette tapes made between 1974 and 1993.
  - COIT 2nd Session NOCW, January 1974 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - COIT 2nd Session NOCW, January 1974 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Evolution of Progressive Addition Lens Design, October 1993 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - NCAA Title - Irv Borish - Hall of Fame Tapes, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Video Recordings
  This series contains eight VHS tapes recorded between August 1984 and January 1990. Three of the tapes contain interview footage of noted optometrists, including Dr. Borish, produced by the American Optometric Association (AOA).
  - Bayshore Lens, August 1984 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Two Hour Tour of China - People to People, October 1985 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - AOA Interviews: Koetting, Stewart, Goodlaw, Baily, Borish, September 1989 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - AOA Interviews: Wechsler, Borish, Grosvenor, Hill, Baily, December 1989 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - AOA Interviews: Wolfberg, Borish Living History of Contact Lenses, January 1990 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - 3rd Symposium International de la Presbytie, undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Auto Refractometer, undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Electronic Refractor, undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
- Miscellaneous
  There are two folders in this series. The items are not dated and consist mostly of sketches of Dr. Borish drawn by students.
  - Sketches by Students, undated (Box 9, Folder 54)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 9, Folder 55)